<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_layout_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2020 The River Developers

    Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
    purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
    copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
    WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
    ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
    OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="let clients propose view positions and dimensions">
    This protocol specifies a way for clients to propose arbitrary positions and
    dimensions for a set of views on a specific output of a compositor through
    the river_layout object.

    This set of views is logically structured as a simple list. Individual views
    in this list can not be addressed. Instead the order of events and requests
    decides which view they concern. This is an intentional limitation.

    The entire set of proposed positions and dimensions for the views in the
    list are called a layout. Due to their list heritage, layouts are also
    logically strictly linear; Any complex underlying data structure a client
    may use when generating the layout is lost in transmission. This is an
    intentional limitation.

    Note that the client may need to handle multiple layout demands per
    river_layout object simultaneously.
  </description>

  <interface name="zriver_layout_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manage river layout objects">
      A global factory for river_layout objects.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_layout_manager object">
        This request indicates that the client will not use the
        river_layout_manager object any more. Objects that have been created
        through this instance are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_river_layout">
      <description summary="create a river_layout object">
        This creates a new river_layout object for the given wl_output.

        All layout related communication is done through this interface.

        The namespace is used by the compositor to decide which river_layout
        object will receive layout demands for the output. Namespaces must be
        unique per output. The same namespace may occur on other outputs, as
        long as that river_layout object comes from the same client. If the
        namespace is found to not obey these uniqueness rules, the server will
        send a namespace_in_use event on the river_layout object immediately
        after creation and ignore all requests on the object aside from the
        destroy request.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zriver_layout_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
      <arg name="namespace" type="string" summary="namespace of the layout object"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zriver_layout_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="receive and respond to layout demands">
      This interface allows clients to receive layout demands from the
      compositor for a specific output and subsequently propose positions and
      dimensions of individual views.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="proposed_dimension_mismatch" value="0" summary="amount of
        proposed dimensions does not match amount of views in layout"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_layout object">
        This request indicates that the client will not use the river_layout
        object any more.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="namespace_in_use">
      <description summary="namespace already in use">
        The requested namespace is already used by another river_layout object.
        After receiving this event, the client should destroy the river_layout
        object. Any other request will be ignored.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="layout_demand">
      <description summary="the compositor is in demand of a layout">
        The compositor raises this event to inform the client that it requires a
        layout for a set of views.

        The usable width and height height indicate the space in which the
        client can safely position views without interfering with desktop
        widgets such as panels.

        The serial of this event is used to identify subsequent events and
        request as belonging to this layout demand. Beware that the client
        might need to handle multiple layout demands at the same time.

        The server will ignore responses to all but the most recent
        layout_demand. Thus, clients should only respond to the most recent
        layout_demand received. If a newer layout_demand is received before the
        client has finished responding to an old demand, the client should
        abort. Work on the old demand as any further work would be wasted.
      </description>
      <arg name="view_amount" type="uint" summary="amount of views in the logical view list and therefore the layout"/>
      <arg name="usable_width" type="uint" summary="width of usable area on output"/>
      <arg name="usable_height" type="uint" summary="height of usable area on output"/>
      <arg name="tags" type="uint" summary="tags of output, 32-bit bitfield"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of demand"/>
    </event>

    <event name="advertise_view">
      <description summary="make layout client aware of view">
        This event is raised by the compositor after a layout_demand event.
        It contains additional information about one out of the set of views
        for which a layout has been demanded.

        It is guaranteed that every view in the layout will be advertised
        exactly once, in the exact order of the view list.

        A client not interested in the additional information may ignore this
        event.

        The serial is the same as that of the layout demand this event belongs
        to.
      </description>
      <arg name="tags" type="uint" summary="bitfield, active tags of view"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string" summary="view app-id" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout demand"/>
    </event>

    <event name="advertise_done">
      <description summary="all views have been advertised">
        The compositor raises this event when it has advertised the entire set
        of views for which a layout has been demanded.

        A client not interested in the additional information may ignore this
        event.

        The serial is the same as that of the layout demand this event belongs
        to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout demand"/>
    </event>

    <request name="push_view_dimensions">
      <description summary="propose view dimensions">
        The client may use this request to push a view dimension proposal to the
        layout.

        View dimension proposals apply to the views in order of the view list.
        As an example, the first push_view_dimensions request will always affect
        the first view in the list.

        A client must propose position and dimensions for the entire set of
        views. Proposing to many or to few view dimensions is a protocol error.

        This request may be sent before the corresponding view has been
        advertised.

        The compositor will transpose the dimensions so that 0 aligns with the
        origin of the usable width and height.

        The serial is used to identify the layout demand this request is a
        response to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout demand"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="x coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="y coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="width of view"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="height of view"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit a layout">
        The client may use this request to signal the compositor that it has
        finished proposing a layout.

        Sending this request irrevocably marks the layout as finished and the
        layout demand will no longer be active. The client may not send any
        other responses to it, doing so is a protocol error.

        Beware that there are no guarantees that the proposed layout will be
        used, the compositor may silently ignore it.

        The serial is used to identify the layout demand this request is a
        response to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout demand"/>
    </request>

    <request name="parameters_changed">
      <description summary="parameters of layout have changed">
        The client may use this request to inform the compositor that one or
        muliple of the parameters it uses to generate layouts have changed.

        If the client is responsible for the current view layout, the compositor
        may decide to send a new layout demand to update the layout.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
